Now, we are going to move on to friction,
and
we are going to continue the problem that
we
left off in the previous videos. So, let's
go
back and quickly redraw the free-body
diagram
we have drawn. So, there is going to be a
force
of gravity, Fg, there is going to be a
normal
force, Fn, F applied, and there will be
a friction force. Now, we are going to
identify
which forces form an action-reaction pair
according
to Newton's third law. So, in case you
guys
forgot what's Newton's third law, I have
it
up here. For every action, there is an
equal
and opposite reaction, and that typically
occurs
on two different objects.
For example, if you punch a piece of wood,
the
two objects being analyzed here are your
hand
and that piece of wood. If you catch a
baseball,
it would be your hand and a baseball. It's
never
on one object. So, with that in mind, I
can
only think of one action-reaction pair on
the
physical level, and that would be the
table
and the box regarding the force of
friction.
This is because the table exerts a force
of
friction on the box, and that box exerts
the
same force of friction on the table, and
that's
just the definition of an action-reaction
pair.
So, next question. Determine whether the
car
accelerates or moves with constant
velocity.
Well, this one, we have to know, first of
all,
how to do the force of friction. The force
of
friction is really, really simple. It's
just
one straightforward formula. Force of
friction
equals normal force, or f of n or n, f of
n
times mu, where f of n is normal force and
mu is the coefficient of friction, which
is
usually given. The coefficient of friction
always determined experimentally in real
life.
There is no shortcut or a formula to
derive
the coefficient of friction. Everything we
know
about the coefficient of friction is
derived
experimentally. That's a fun fact, and
yeah,
this is basically the main formula for
today's
video, and we are going to put it in good
use.
So, determine whether the car accelerates
or
moves with constant velocity. Well, in
order
to do that, we have to know about and
calculate
the net force. The net force is basically
the
overall force that an object undergoes, so
all
these forces combined. Well, first of all,
the
combination of the normal force and the
force
of gravity cross out, so the net force
going
up and down vertically is zero.
There's no net force going up and down.
The
box stays where it is. However,
horizontally,
it's a different story. The net force, if
we
treat to the right as the positive
direction,
it's the applied force subtracted by the
force
of friction, because the force of friction
is
going here, so f app minus f app, and
getting
the net force is crucial, and it's
basically
the start to every dynamics problem.
You have to get the overall force that the
object
undergoes to even know and comprehend how
it's
going to move. In this case, it's pretty
simple.
The applied force, we know it is 18
newtons.
The force of friction is, we know the
normal
force. The normal force is positive
because
it's going up, and it's the magnitude of
gravity,
which is mass of the crate times the
acceleration
to gravity, and now that's our normal
force,
and now we have to have the coefficient of
friction,
so times mu, so it'd just be 18 minus 5.0
times
9.81 times the coefficient is 0.30.
And we should get around 3.2, 3.3
because of sig figs, 3.3 newtons.
And keep in mind that it's positive, which
means
the net force is going that way with a
magnitude
of 3.3 newtons. And what does that tell
us?
Well, that means that the box undergoes a
constant
force of 3.3 newtons to the right, and
that's
its overall force. All of these forces
combine
to make an overall force going 3.3 newtons
to
the right, and no other force matters
unless
there's an external force, as we talked
about.
So what does that mean? Well, that means
that
it's going to accelerate.
Why? Because there is constant force
applied
to this, and force is mass times
acceleration.
If this is constant, then acceleration
will
be constant. There will be a constant
acceleration
being undergone by the box, and
that will be the answer to that part.
Calculate the magnitude and direction of
the
acceleration. Well, we already did 70% of
problem by calculating this force.
So how about you first pause the video and
try
doing this question, and we'll take it up.
Okay, so now what we have is we have f net
is
equal to the mass times acceleration, the
net
acceleration of the object. We have f net
over
here, and we want to calculate the
acceleration.
Do we have the mass? Yes, we do. The mass
is
given in the problem, and it says 5
kilograms.
Acceleration, a net.
So what would the acceleration be? Well,
we
just isolate for it. It's f net over m 3.3
over
5, and that would give you 3.3 divided by
5,
0.66 metres per second squared.
And it also asks you to put a direction.
We know it's positive, which means it's
going
to this way, which is to the right.
The question didn't specify, so we're just
going
to say it goes in the positive direction,
because
this is positive. Oh, it does say to the
right.
So yeah, it's going to be towards the
Right. And that will be your answer for
this
question. Oh, that's an ugly box.
And that's basically it for the force of
friction,
and we went a little extra, and we talked
about
how to do these types of dynamics
problems.
Basically, the number one tip I'm going to
give
you here is to always try to find the net
force.
Always, always, always try to find the net
force,
even if it's in components.
If you're dealing with harder questions,
you
might have to find the net force
horizontally
and the net force vertically separately,
and
then you can deal with those numbers
later.
But you have to combine vectors to get the
overall
motion that the object is undergoing.
And yeah, that's it for the force of
friction
and an introduction to how to solve real
dynamics
problems. Thank you.